## Matthew K. Perez

3844 Bob and Betty Beyster Building, Ann Arbor, MI 48103 Email: mkperez@umich.edu | Phone: (808) 286-4393 Website: https://matthewkperez.com/

#### RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interests center around leveraging the rich signal of human speech for characterizing health, behavior, and mood using machine learning models. My research has touched on various topics, including automatic speech recognition, speech synthesis, acoustic feature analysis, and computational paralinguistics. My thesis work largely involves developing novel approaches to enable individuals with speech impairments to communicate effectively, which has driven my passion for advancing the field of speech technology to benefit a broader range of populations.

#### **EDUC**

EDUCATION	
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering Advisor: Dr. Emily Mower Provost	2017 – 2023 (expected)
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor M.S. in Computer Science and Engineering Advisor: Dr. Emily Mower Provost	2017 – 2019
University of Notre Dame B.S. in Computer Science, Cum Laude	2013 – 2017
AWARDS	
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP)	2020 - 2023
GEM Ph.D. Engineering Fellowship	2019 - 2020
Dean's List, University of Notre Dame	2015 - 2017
Balfour-Hesburgh Scholar, University of Notre Dame	2013 - 2017

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Computational Human Artificial Intelligence (CHAI) Lab	2017 – Present
University of Michigan	Ann Arbor, MI

Working on speech and signal processing methods for analyzing various neurological conditions.

### Research Assistant: Mobile Computing Lab

2015-2016

University of Notre Dame

Notre Dame, IN

Investigated speech analysis methods for classifying mild traumatic brain injuries (concussions).

### **PUBLICATIONS**

Yang Yu, Matthew Perez, Ankur Bapna, Fadi Haik, Siamak Tazari, Yu Zhang. "PronScribe: Highly accurate multimodal phonemic transcription from speech and text". Interspeech 2023 (In submission)

James Tavernor, Matthew Perez, Emily Mower Provost. "Episodic Memory For Domain-Adaptable, Robust Speech Emotion Recognition". Interspeech 2023 (In submission)

Matthew Perez, Mimansa Jaiswal, Minx Niu, Cristina Gorrostieta, Matthew Roddy, Kye Taylor, Reza Lotfian, John Kane, Emily Mower Provost. "Mind the gap: On the value of silence representations to lexical-based speech emotion recognition". Interspeech 2022. (poster presentation)

Amrit Romana, Minxue Niu, Matthew Perez, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Enabling Off-the-Shelf Disfluency Detection and Categorization for Pathological Speech". Interspeech 2022. (oral presentation)

Matthew Perez, Amrit Romana, Noelle Carlozzi, Prayeen Dayalu, Jennifer Ann Miner, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Articulatory Coordination for Speech Motor Tracking in Huntington Disease" Interspeech 2021. (oral presentation)

Amrit Romana, John Bandon, **Matthew Perez**, Stephanie Gutierrez, Richard Richter, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Automatically Detecting Errors and Disfluencies in Read Speech to Predict Cognitive Impairment in People with Parkinson's Disease". Interspeech 2021 (oral presentation)

Zakaria Aldeneh, **Matthew Perez**, and Emily Mower Provost. "Learning Paralinguistic Features from Audiobooks through Style Voice Conversion" NAACL 2021. (*virtual presentation*)

**Matthew Perez**, Zakaria Aldeneh, and Emily Mower Provost. "Aphasic Speech Recognition using a Mixture of Speech Intelligibility Experts" Interspeech 2020. (*virtual presentation*)

**Matthew Perez**, Wenyu Jin, Duc Le, Noelle Carlozzi, Praveen Dayalu, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Classification of Huntington's Disease Using Acoustic and Lexical Features." Interspeech 2018. (*oral presentation*)

Louis Daudet, Nikhil Yadav, **Matthew Perez**, Christian Poellabauer, Sandra Schneider, Alan Huebner. "Portable mTBI Assessment Using Temporal and Frequency Analysis of Speech." IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics 2017.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Intern 2022

Google Mountain View, CA

Worked on frontend text-to-speech focusing on fine-tuning end-to-end networks for pronunciation learning.

**Research Intern**Cogito Corporation
Virtual

Worked on the Speech Signals team where I researched learning silence tokens within a language modeling framework (GloVe/BERT) for speech emotion recognition.

Research Intern 2019

MIT Lincoln Laboratory

Lexington, MA

Worked with Thomas Quatieri in the Bioengineering and Technologies Systems Group where my research focused on analyzing speech-based articulation features for neurological diseases such as depression.

iOS Developer Intern 2016

Garmin Olathe, KS

Contributed to the development of the Garmin iOS application, which syncs wearable device data to/from the iPhone. Specifically, implemented *Today Extensions* for the Garmin Connect Mobile app, which displays wearable health information like steps, activities, etc. I presented work to research teams and company executives.

#### **Software Developer: ND Tours**

Graduate Engineering Research Symposium, Ann Arbor

2016

University of Notre Dame

Notre Dame, IN

Developed mobile app using augmented reality that overlays the camera view with the history and information about specific landmarks. Coded in objective-c and uses firebase for backend location and data storage.

#### **TALKS**

Learning silence in language models for speech emotion recognition Google-Speech Reading Group, Mountain View	2022
Speech Intelligibility in Aphasic Speech Recognition Modeling The National GEM Consortium Technical Workshop, Virtual	2020
Multimodal Classification of Huntington Disease, Student Poster Award	2018

## **SERVICES**

Reviewer, Transactions on Audio, Speech and Language Processing	2023
Reviewer, Transactions of Affective Computing	2023
Reviewer, Affective Computing & Intelligent Interaction (ACII)	2021
Reviewer, Computer Speech & Language	2020
Poster Chair, Michigan AI Symposium University of Michigan, Ann Arbor	2019

## **MEMBERSHIP**

BERSHIP	
Member, International Speech Communication Association	2018 – Present
Member, IEEE	2016 – Present
National GEM Fellow	2019 – Present

# **SKILLS**

Languages: Python, Bash, C++, Objective-C Software Frameworks: Kaldi, Speechbrain, Pytorch-kaldi, OpenSmile, Librosa, NumPy, Pandas

Machine Learning: Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, scikit-learn